room CHAPTER 11 For years, Dorian Gray could not free himself from the influence of this book.
Or perhaps it would be more accurate to say that he never sought to free himself
from it. He procured from Paris no less than n large paper copies of the first
edition, and had them bound in different colors so that they might suit his
various moods and the changing fancies of a nature over which he seemed, at
times, to have almost entirely lost control. The hero, the wonderful young
Parisian in whom the romantic and the scientific temperaments were so strangely
blended, became to him a kind of prefiguring type of himself and And, indeed, the whole book
seemed to him to contain the story of his own life, written before he had lived
it. In one point he was more fortunate than the novel’s fantastic hero. He never
knew— —never, indeed, had any cause to know— —that somewhat grotesque dread of mirrors,
and polished metal surfaces, and still water which came upon the young Parisian
so early in his life, and was occasioned by the sudden decay of a bow that had
once appar apparently, been so remarkable.
It was with an almost cruel joy— —and perhaps in nearly every joy, as certainly
in every pleasure, cruelty has its place— —that he used to read the latter part of
the book, with its really tragic, if somewhat overemphasized, account of the sorrow and
despair of one who had himself lost what in others, and the world, he had most dearly
valued. For the wonderful beauty that had so fascinated Basil hallwood and many
others besides him, seemed never to leave him. Even those who had heard the most
evil things against him— —and from time to time strange rumors about his mode of
life crept through London and became the chatter of the clubs— —could not believe
anything to his dishonor when they saw him. He had always the look of one who
had kept himself unspotted from the world. Men who talked grossly became
silent when Dorian Gray entered the room.
There was something in the purity of his face that rebuked them. His mere presence
seemed to recall to them the memory of the innocence that they had
tarnished. They wondered how one so charming and graceful as he was could
have escaped the stain of an age that was at once sorted and
sensual. Often, on returning home from one of those mysterious and prolonged
absences that gave rise to such strange conjecture among those who were his
friends, or thought that they were so, he himself would creep up upstairs to the
locked room, open the door with the key that never left him now, and stand, with a
mirror, in front of the portrait that Basil hallwood had painted of him,
looking now at the evil and aging face on the canvas, and now at the fair young
face that laughed back at him from the polished glass. The very sharpness of the
contrast used to quicken his sense of pleasure. He grew more and more enamored
of his own beauty, more and more interested in the corruption of his own
soul. He would examine with minute care, and sometimes with a monstrous and
terrible delight, the hideous lines that seared the wrinkling forehead or crawled
around the heavy sensual mouth, wondering sometimes which were the more horrible,
the signs of sin or the signs of age. He would place his white hands
beside the coarse bloated hands of the picture, and smile. He mocked the misshapen body and
the failing limbs.
There were moments, indeed, at night, when, lying sleepless in his own delicately
scented chamber, or in the sorted room of the little ill-fame tavern near the
docks which, under an assumed name and in disguise, it was his habit to frequent, he
would think of the ruin he had brought upon his soul with a pity that was all
the more poignant because it was purely selfish. But moments such as these were
rare. That curiosity about life which Lord Henry had first stirred in him him,
as they sat together in the garden of their friend, seemed to increase with
gratification. The more he knew, the more he desired to know. He had mad hungers
that grew more ravenous as he fed them. Yet he was not really reckless, at
any rate in his relations to society. Once or twice every month during
the winter, and on each Wednesday evening while the season lasted, he would throw
open to the world his beautiful house and have the most celebrated musicians
of the day to charm his guests with the wonders of their art. His little dinners,
in the settling of which Lord Henry always assisted him, were noted as much
for the careful selection and placing of those invited, as for the exquisite taste
shown in the decoration of the table, with its subtle symphonic arrangements
of exotic flowers, and embroidered cloths, and antique plate of gold and
silver. Indeed, there were many, especially among the very young men, who
saw, or fancied that they saw, in Dorian Gray the true realization of a type of
which they had often dreamed in Eaton or Oxford days, a type that was to combine
something of the real culture of the scholar with all the grace and
distinction and perfect manner of a citizen of the world. To them he seemed to be of the
company of those whom Dante describes as having sought to “make themselves perfect
by the worship of beauty.” Like gotier he was one for whom “the visible world
existed.” And, certainly, to him life itself was the first, the greatest, of the arts,
and for it all the other arts seemed to be but a preparation. Fashion, by which what is
really fantastic becomes for a moment universal, and dandism which, in its own
way, is an attempt to assert the absolute modernity of beauty, had, of course, their
fascination for him. His mode of dressing, and the particular styles that from time
to time he affected, had their marked influence on the young exquisites of the
Mayfair balls and palm club windows, who copied him in everything that he did, and
tried to reproduce the accidental charm of his graceful, though to him only half serious
feries For, while he was but too ready to accept the position that was almost
immediately offered to him on his coming of age, and found, indeed, a subtle
pleasure in the thought that he might really become to the London of his own
day what to imperial Neronian Rome the author of the satiric con once had
been, yet in his inmost heart he desired to be something more than a mere arbiter
elegantiarum to be consulted on the wearing of a jewel, or the knotting of a
necktie, or the conduct of a cane. He sought to elaborate some new scheme of
life that would have its reasoned philosophy and its ordered principles, and find in the
spiritualizing of the senses its highest realization. The worship of the senses
has often, and with much justice, been decried, men feeling a natural instinct
of terror about passions and sensations that seem stronger than themselves, and
that they are conscious of sharing with the less highly organized forms of
existence. But it appeared to Dorian Gray that the true nature of the senses had
never been understood, and that they had remained savage an animal merely because
the world had sought to starve them into submission or to kill them by pain,
instead of aiming at making them elements of a new spirituality, of which
a fine instinct for beauty was to be the dominant characteristic. As he looked back upon
man moving through history, he was haunted by a feeling of loss. So much had
been surrendered! and to such little purpose! There had been mad willful rejections,
monstrous forms of self-torture and self-denial, whose origin was fear and
whose result was a degradation infinitely more terrible than that fancy
degradation from which, in their ignorance, they had sought to escape;
Nature, in her wonderful irony, driving out the anchorite to feed with the wild
animals of the desert and giving to the hermit the beasts of the field as his
companions. Yes: there was to be, as Lord Henry had had prophesied, a new Hedonism
that was to recreate life and to save it from that harsh uncomely puritanism that
is having, in our own day, its curious revival. It was to have its service of
the intellect, certainly, yet it was never to accept any theory or system that
would involve the sacrifice of any mode of passionate experience. Its aim, indeed, was to be
experience itself, and not the fruits of experience, sweet or bitter as they might
be. Of the asceticism that deadens the senses, as of the vulgar profligacy that
dulls them, it was to know nothing. But it was to teach man to concentrate himself
upon the moments of a life that is itself but a
moment. There are few of us who have not sometimes wakened before dawn, either
after one of those dreamless nights that make us almost enamored of death, or one
of those nights of horror and misshapen joy, when through the chambers of the
brain sweep phantoms more terrible than reality itself, and instinct with that
vivid life that lurks in all grotesques, and that lends to Gothic art its
enduring vitality, this art being, one might fancy, especially the art of those
whose minds have been troubled with the malady of revery Gradually white fingers
creep through the curtains, and they appear to tremble. In black fantastic
shapes, dumb shadows crawl into the corners of the room and crouch
there. Outside, there is the stirring of birds among the leaves, or the sound of
men going forth to their work, or the sigh and sob of the wind coming down
from the hills and wandering around the silent house, as though it feared to wake
the sleepers and yet must needs call forth sleep from her purple cave. Veil
after veil of thin dusky gwes is lifted, and by degrees the forms and colors of
things are restored to them, and we watch the dawn remaking the world in its
antique pattern. The one mirrors get back their mimic life. The flameless tapers
stand where we had left them, and beside them lies the half cut book that we had
been studying, or the wired flower that we had worn at the ball, or the letter
that we had been afraid to read, or that we had read too often. Nothing seems to us
changed. Out of the unreal shadows of the night comes back the real life that we had
known. We have to resume it where we had left off, and there steals over us a
terrible sense of the necessity for the continuance of energy in the same
wearisome round of stereotyped habits, or a wild longing, it may be, that our
eyelids might open some morning upon a world that had been refashioned a new in
the darkness for our pleasure, a world in which things would have fresh shapes and
colors and be changed, or have other secrets, a world in which the past would
have little or no place, or survive, at any rate, in no conscious form of
obligation or regret, the remembrance even of joy having its bitterness and
the memories of pleasure their pain. It was the creation of such worlds
as these that seemed to Dorian Gray to be the true object, or amongst the true
objects, of life; and in his search for sensations that would be at once new and
delightful, and possess that element of strangeness that is so essential to
romance, he would often adopt certain modes of thought that he knew to be
really alien to his nature, abandon himself to their subtle influences, and
then, having, as it were, caught their color and satisfied his intellectual
curiosity, leave them with that curious indifference that is not incompatible
with a real ardor of temperament, and that, indeed, according to certain modern
psychologists, is often a condition of it. It was rumored of him once that he
was about to join the Roman Catholic communion, and certainly the Roman ritual
had always a great attraction for him.
The daily sacrifice, more awful really than all the sacrifices of the antique
world, stirred him as much by its superb rejection of the evidence of the senses
as by the primitive simplicity of its elements and the eternal pathos of the
human tragedy that it sought to symbolize. He loved to kneel down on the
cold marble pavement and watch the priest, in his stiff flowered dalmatic,
slowly and with white hands moving aside the veil of the tabernacle, or raising
aoft the jeweled lantern-shaped monstrance with that palid wafer that at
times, one would fain think, is indeed the panis cistus the bread of angels, or,
robed in the garments of the Passion of Christ, breaking the Host in to the
chalice and smiting his breast for his sins. The fuming senses that the grave
boys, in their lace and scarlet, tossed into the air like great guilt flowers
had their subtle fascination for him. As he passed out, he used to look with
wonder at the black confessionals and long to sit in the dim shadow of one of
them and listen to men and women whispering through the worn grating the true story of their
lives. But he never fell into the error of arresting his intellectual
development by any formal acceptance of creed or system, or of mistaking, for a
house in which to live, an inn that is but suitable for the sourn of a night, or
for a few hours of a night in which there are no stars and the moon is in
travail. Mysticism, with its marvelous power of making common things strange to
us, and the subtle antinomianism that always seems to accompany it, moved him
for a season; and for a season he inclined to the materialistic doctrines
of the Darwinism movement in Germany, and found a curious pleasure in tracing the
thoughts and passions of men to some pearly cell in the brain, or some white
nerve in the body, delighting in the conception of the absolute dependence of
the spirit on certain physical conditions, morbid or healthy, normal or
diseased. Yet, as has been said of him before, no theory of life seemed to him
to be of any importance compared with life itself. He felt keenly conscious of how
barren all intellectual speculation is when separated from action and
experiment. He knew that the senses, no less than the soul, have their spiritual mysteries to
reveal. And so he would now study perfumes and the secrets of their
manufacturer distilling heavily scented oils and burning odorous gums from the
East. He saw that there was no mood of the mind that had not its counterpart in
the sensuous life, and set himself to discover their true relations, wondering
what there was in frankincense that made one mystical, and in ambergis that
stirred one’s passions, and in violets that woke the memory of dead romances,
and in musk that troubled the brain, and in shac that stained the imagination; and
seeking often to elaborate a real psychology of perfumes, and to estimate
the several influ fluences of sweet smelling roots and scented pollen Laden
flowers; of aromatic balms and of dark and fragrant woods; of spikenard, that
sickens; of hovenia, that makes men mad; and of aloras that are said to be able
to expel melancholy from the soul. At another time he devoted himself
entirely to music, and in a long laed room, with a Vermilion and gold ceiling
and walls of olive green lacquer, he used to give curious concerts in
which mad gypsies tore wild music from little zithers, or grave yellow Shaw
Tunisians plucked at the strained strings of monstrous loots while
grinning Negroes beat monotonously upon copper drums and, crouching upon scarlet
mats, slim turbaned Indians blew through long pipes of reed or brass and charmed—
—or faine to charm— —great hooded snakes and horrible horned
adders. The harsh intervals and shrill discords of barbaric music stirred him
at times when Schubert’s grace, and Chan's beautiful sorrows, and the mighty
harmonies of bethoven himself, fell unheeded on his ear. He collected together from all parts
of the world the strangest instruments that could be found, either in the tombs
of dead nations or among the few savage tribes that have survived contact with Western
civilizations, and love to touch and try them. He had the mysterious jurupari of
the Rio Negro Indians, that women are not allowed to look at and that even youths
may not see till they have been subjected to fasting and scourging, and
the earn jars of the Peruvians that have the shrill cries of birds, and fluts of
human bones such as Alfonso de oal heard in Chile, and the sonorous green jaspers
that are found near Cusco and give forth a note of singular sweetness.
He had painted gourds filled with pebbles that rattled when they were
shaken; the long clarine of the Mexicans, into which the performer does not blow,
but through which he inhales the air; the harsh T of the Amazon tribes, that is
sounded by the sentinels who sit all day long in high trees, and can be heard, it
is said, at a distance of three leagues; the tastle that has two vibrating
tongues of wood and is beaten with sticks that are smeared with an elastic
gum obtained from the milky juice of plants; the yotel bells of the Aztecs,
that are hung in clusters like grapes; and a huge cylindrical drum, covered with
the skins of great serpents, like the one that Bernal Diaz saw when he went with
Cortez into the Mexican temple, and of whose doleful sound he has left us so vivid a
description. The fantastic character of these instruments fascinated him, and he
felt a curious delight in the thought that AR Heart like Nature, has her
monsters, things of bestial shape and with hideous voices. Yet, after some time, he wearied of
them, and would sit in his box at the opera, either alone or with Lord Henry,
listening in wrapped pleasure to tanhauser and seeing in the prelude to
that great work of art a presentation of the tragedy of his own
soul. On one occasion he took up the study of jewels, and appeared at a
costume ball as de joers Admiral of France, in a dress covered with 560
pearls. This taste enthralled him for years, and, indeed, may be said never to
have left him. He would often spend a whole day settling and resettling in
their cases the various stones that he had collected, such as the olive green
chrisser Barrel that turns red by lamp light the simane with its wirelike line
of silver, the pistachio colored parador Rose pink and wine yellow tazes
carbuncles of fiery scarlet with tremulous four raid stars flame red
cinnamon Stones orange and violet spinels, and amethysts with their alternate layers of ruby and
sapphire. He loved the red gold of the sunstone, and the Moonstone pearly
whiteness, and the broken rainbow of the milky opal. He procured from Amsterdam three
emeralds of extraordinary size and Rich n of color and had a turquoise davier
Ros that was the envy of all the connoisseurs. He discovered wonderful
stories, also, about jewels. In Alfonso's clerical Disciplina a serpent was
mentioned with eyes of real jacinth, and in the romantic history of Alexander, the
Conqueror of emtha was said to have found in the veil of Jordan snakes “with
collars of real emeralds growing on their backs.” There was a gem in the brain
of the dragon fil estratus told us, and “by the exhibition of golden letters and
a scarlet robe” the monster could be thrown into a magical sleep and slain.
According to the great alchemist, Pierre de bonifas the diamond rendered a man
invisible, and the agate of India made him eloquent. The cornelian appeased
anger, and the hyasynth provoked sleep, and the amethyst drove away the fumes of
wine. The garnet cast out demons, and the hydropic deprived the moon of her
color The selenite waxed and waned with the moon, and the melus that discovers
thieves, could be affected only by the blood of kids leonardis camilus had seen a white
stone taken from the brain of a newly killed toad, that was a certain antidote against
poison. The bizor that was found in the heart of the Arabian deer, was a charm
that could cure the plague.
In the nests of Arabian birds was the aspirates that, according to democratus
kept the wearer from any danger by fire. The King of Salan rode through his
city with a large ruby in his hand, as the ceremony of his
coronation. The gates of the palace of John the Priest were “made of sardius,
with the horn of the horn snake INR so that no man might bring poison
within.” Over the gable were “two golden apples, in which were two carbunkle so
that the gold might shine by day and the carbunkle by night. In Lodge’s strange romance ‘A
Margarite of America’, it was stated that in the chamber of the queen one could
behold “all the chased ladies of the world in chased out of silver, looking
through fair mirrors of chryses carbuncles, sapphires, and green emerals Marco Polo had seen the
inhabitants of Zipangu place rose-colored pearls in the mouths
of the dead. A sea monster had been enamored of the pearl that the diver
brought to King per Roes and had slain the thief, and mourned for seven moons over its
loss. When the Huns lured the king into the great pit, he flung it away— —Procopius
tells the story— —nor was it ever found again, though the Emperor Anastasius
offered 500 weight of gold pieces for it.
The King of Mal alabar had shown to a certain Venetian a rosary of 304 pearls,
one for every god that he worshiped When the Duke de Valentinois,
son of Alexander V 6 visited Louis I 12th of France, his horse was loaded with
gold leaves, according to Bronto and his cap had double rows of
rubies that threw out a great light.
Charles of England had ridden in stirrups hung with 421 diamonds. Richard
the second had a coat, valued at 30,000 marks, which was covered with balas
rubies. Hall described Henry VII on his way to the Tower previous to his
coronation, as wearing “a jacket of raised gold, the placard embroidered with
diamonds and other rich stones, and a great bodder about his neck of large
baces The favorites of James I wore earrings of emeralds set in gold Philly
grin Edward II gave to Pier Gaveston a suit of red gold armor studded with
Yasin a collar of gold roses set with turquoise stones and a skullcap parm with pearls. Henry
II. wore jeweled gloves reaching to the elbow, and had a hawk glove sewn with 12
rubies and 52 great Oran The ducal hat of Charles the Rash, the last Duke of
Burgundy of his race, was hung with pear-shaped pearls and studded with
sapphires. How exquisite life had once been! How gorgeous in its pomp and
decoration! Even to read of the luxury of the dead was wonderful. Then he turned his attention
to embroideries and to the tapestries that performed the office of Fresco in
the chill rooms of the northern nations of Europe. As he investigated the subject—
—and he always had an extraordinary faculty of becoming absolutely absorbed
for the moment in whatever he took up— —he was almost saddened by the reflection of
the ruin that time brought on beautiful and wonderful things. He, at any rate, had
escaped that. Summer followed summer, and the yellow jonquils bloomed and died
many times, and nights of horror repeated the story of their shame, but he was
unchanged. No winter marred his face or stained his flowerlike bloom. How
different it was with material things!
Where had they passed to? Where was the great crocus color robe, on which the
gods fought against the giants, that had been worked by brown girls for the pleasure of
Athena? Where the huge valarium that Nero had stretched across the Coliseum at
Rome, that Titan sail of purple on which was represented the starry sky, and
Apollo driving a chariot drawn by white guilt rained steeds? He longed to see the curious
table napkins wrought for the Priest of the Sun, on which were displayed all the
dainties and beans that could be wanted for a feast; the Mory cloth of King chil
prick with its 300 golden bees; the fantastic robes that excited the
indignation of the Bishop of Pontus and were figured with “lions, panthers, bears,
dogs, forests, rocks, hunters— —all, in fact, that a painter can copy from nature”; and
the coat that Charles of oron once wore, on the sleeves of which were embroidered
the verses of a song beginning Madame Jer the musical accp of the words being
wrought in gold thread, and each note, of square shape in those days, formed with four
pearls. He read of the room that was prepared at the palace at rames for the
use of Queen Joan of Burgundy and was decorated with 1321 parrots, made embroidery and
blazoned with the king’s arms, and 561 butterflies, whose wings were similarly
ornamented with the arms of the queen, the whole world in gold karinda Medicis had a morning bed
made for her of black velvet powdered with crants and suns. Its curtains were
of damus with leafy wreaths and garlands, figured upon a gold and silver ground,
and fringed along the edges with broidery of pearls, and it stood in a
room hung with rows of the queen’s devices in cut black velvet upon cloth of
silver. Louis the 14th had gold embroidered car Mar aades 15 ft high in
his apartment. The state bed of seski King of Poland, was made of Smyrna gold
brickade embroidered in turquoises with verses from the Quran Its supports were of silver guilt
beautifully chased, and profusely set with enameled and jeweled
medallions. It had been taken from the Turkish camp before Vienna, and the
standard of Muhammad had stood beneath the tremulous guilt of its
canopy. And so, for a whole year, he sought to accumulate the most exquisite
specimens that he could find of textile and embroidered work, getting the dainty
Deli muslins, finely rought with gold thread Palm mates and stitched over with
iridescent beetles’ wings; the daa GES that from their transparency are known
in the East as “woven air,” and “running water,” and “evening dew”; strange figured
cloths from Java; elaborate yellow Chinese hangings book bound in tny
satins or fair blue silks and rought with Flur Dee birds and images; veils of
lasses worked in hungry point; Sicilian brocades and stiff Spanish velvets;
Georgian work, with its guilt coins, and Japanese fukus saas with their green
toned golds and their marvelously plumaged birds. He had a special passion, also, for
ecclesiastical vestments, as indeed he had for everything connected with the
service of the the Church. In the long cedar chests that lined the west gallery
of his house, he had stored away many rare and beautiful specimens of what is
really the rment of the Bride of Christ, who must wear purple and jewels and fine
linen that she may hide the palid mated body that is worn by the suffering that
she seeks for and wounded by self-inflicted pain. He possessed a
gorgeous cope of crimson silk and gold thread damus figured with a repeating
pattern of golden pomegranates set in six petal formal blossoms, beyond which
on either side was the pineapple device wrought in seed pearls The ores were divided into panels
representing scenes from the life of the Virgin, and the coronation of the Virgin
was figured in colored silks upon the hood. This was Italian work of the 15th
century. Another cope was of green velvet, embroidered with heart-shaped groups of a canthus
leaves from which spread long stemmed white blossoms, the details of which were
picked out with silver thread and colored crystals. The morse bore a serap's head
in Gold thread raised work. The orre were woven in a diaper of red and gold silk,
and were starred with medallions of many saints and martyrs, among whom was St.
Sebastian. He had Chaz also, of amber colored silk, and blue silk and gold
brade and yellow silk damask and cloth of gold, figured with representations of
the Passion and Crucifixion of Christ, and embroidered with lions and peacocks
and other emblems; dalmatics of white satin and pink silk damask, decorated
with tulips and dolphins and Flur Dee alter frontals of crimson velvet and
blue linen; and many corporals chalice veils and sudaria. In the mystic offices to which
such things were put, there was something that quickened his
imagination. For these treasures, and everything that he collected in his
lovely house, were to be to him means of forgetfulness, modes by which he could
escape, for a season, from the fear that seemed to him at times to be almost too
great to be born Upon the walls of the lonely locked
room where he had spent so much of his boyhood, he had hung with his own hands
the terrible portrait whose changing features showed him the real degradation
of his life, and in front of it had draped the purple and gold Paul as a
curtain. For weeks he would not go there, would forget the hideous painted thing,
and get back his light heart, his wonderful joyousness, his passionate absorption in mere
existence. Then, suddenly, some night he would creep out of the house, go down to
dreadful places near Blu Gate Fields, and stay there, day after day, until he was driven away.
On his return he would sit in front of the picture, sometimes loathing it and
himself, but filled, at other times, with that pride of individualism that is half
the fascination of sin, and smiling with secret pleasure at the Miss shape and
shadow that had to bear the burden that should have been his
own. After a few years he could not endure to be long out of England, and
gave up the villa that he had shared at trille with Lord Henry, as well as the
little white wall in house at alers where they had more than once spent the
winter. He hated to be separated from the picture that was such a part of his life,
and was also afraid that during his absence someone might gain access to the
room, in spite of the elaborate bars that he had caused to be placed upon the
door. He was quite conscious that this would tell them nothing. It was true that the portrait
still preserved, under all the foulness and ugliness of the face, its marked
likeness to himself; but what could they learn from that? He would laugh at anyone
who tried to taunt him. He had not painted it. What was it to him how vile
and full of shame it looked? Even if he told them, would they believe it? Yet he was
afraid. Sometimes when he was down at his great house in Nottinghamshire,
entertaining the fashionable young men of his own rank who were his chief
companions, and astounding the county by the wanten luxury and gorgeous Splendor
of his mode of of life, he would suddenly leave his guests and rush back to town
to see that the door had not been tampered with and that the picture was still
there. What if it should be stolen? The mere thought made him cold with horror.
Surely the world would know his secret then. Perhaps the world already suspected
it. For, while he fascinated many, there were not a few who distrusted him. He was
very nearly blackballed at a West club of which his birth and social position
fully entitled him to become a member, and it was said that on one occasion,
when he was brought by a friend into the smoking room of the Churchill, the Duke
of Beric and another gentleman got up in a marked manner and went out. Curious
stories became current about him after he had passed his 25th year. It was
rumored that he had been seen brawling with foreign sailors in a low den in the
distant parts of White Chapel and that he consorted with thieves and coiners
and knew the mysteries of their trade. His extraordinary absences became
notorious, and, when he used to reappear again in society, men would whisper to
each other in corners, or pass him with a sneer, or look at him with cold searching
eyes, as though they were determined to discover his secret. Of such insolences and attempted
slights he, of course, took no notice, and in the opinion of most people his friend
frank debonaire manner, his charming boyish smile, and the infinite grace of
that wonderful youth that seemed never to leave him, were in themselves a
sufficient answer to the calumnies, for so they termed them, that were circulated
about him. It was remarked, however, that some of those who had been most intimate
with him appeared, after a time, to shun him. Women who had wildly adored him, and
for his sake had braved all social censure and set convention at defiance,
were seen to grow palid with shame or horror if Dorian Gray entered the
room. Yet these whispered scandals only increased in the eyes of many his
strange and dangerous charm. His great wealth was a certain element of
security. Society— —civilized society, at least— —is never very ready to believe
anything to the detriment of those who are both rich and
fascinating. It feels instinctively that manners are of more importance than
morals, and, in its opinion, the highest respectability is of much less value
than the possession of a good chef And, after all, it is a very poor consolation
to be told that the man who has given one a bad dinner, or poor wine, is
irreproachable in his private life. Even the cardinal virtues cannot atone for
half cold Entre as Lord Henry remarked once, in a discussion on the subject, and
there is possibly a good deal to be said for his view. For for the Cannons of good
society are, or should be, the same as the Cannons of art. Form is absolutely
essential to it. It should have the dignity of a ceremony, as well as its
unreality, and should combine the insincere character of a romantic play
with the wit and beauty that make such plays delightful to us. Is in sincerity
such a terrible thing? I think not. It is merely a method by which we
can multiply our person alities Such, at any rate, was Dorian Gray’s
opinion. He used to wonder at the shallow psychology of those who conceived the
ego in man as a thing simple, permanent, reliable, and of one essence. To him, man
was a being with myriad lives and myriad sensations, a complex multiform creature
that bore within itself strange legacies of thought and passion, and whose very
flesh was tainted with the monstrous maladies of the dead. He loved to stroll
through the gaunt cold picture gallery of his country house and look at the
various portraits of those whose blood flowed in his veins. Here was Philip Herbert, described
by Francis osbor in his Memoirs on the Reigns of Queen Elizabeth and King James,
as one who was “caressed by the Court for his handsome face, which kept him not
long company.” Was it young Herbert’s life that he sometimes led? Had some strange
poisonous germ crept from body to body till it had reached his
own? Was it some dim sense of that ruined grace that had made him so suddenly, and
almost without cause, give utterance, in Basil hallwood studio, to the mad prayer
that had so changed his life? Here, in Gold embroidered red dublet jeweled
surir coat and guilt edged ruff and wristbands, stood Sir Anthony sherod with
his silver and black armor piled at his feet. What had this man’s legacy been? Had
the lover of giovana of Naples bequeathed him some inheritance of sin
and shame? Were his own actions merely the dreams that the dead man had not dared to
realize? Here, from the fading canvas, smiled Lady Elizabeth Dez in her Gau
hood, pearl stomacher, and pink slashed sleeves. A flower was in her right hand,
and her left clasped an enameled collar of white and damus roses. On a table by
her side lay a mandolin and an apple.
There were large green rosettes upon her little pointed shoes. He knew her life,
and the strange stories that were told about her lovers. Had he something of her
temperament in him? These oval heavy lided eyes seemed to look curiously at
him. What of George Willoughby, with his powdered hair and fantastic patches? How
evil he looked! The face was saturnine and sthy and the sensual lips seemed to
be twisted with dis stain Delicate lace ruffles fell over the lean yellow hands
that were so overladen with rings. He had been a maceroni of the 18th century, and
the friend, in his youth, of Lord Farah What of the second Lord Beckham the
companion of the Prince Regent in his wildest days, and one of the witnesses at
the secret marriage with Mrs Fitz Herbert How proud and handsome he was,
with his chestnut curls and insolent pose! What passion had he bequeathed? The
world had looked upon him as infamous. He had led the orgies at Carlton House. The
star of the gter glittered upon his breast. Beside him hung the portrait of
his wife, a palid thin lipped woman in black. Her blood, also, stirred within him.
How curious it all seemed! And his mother with her Lady Hamilton face and her moist wi dashed
lips— —he knew what he had got from from her. He had got from her his beauty, and
his passion for the beauty of others. She laughed at him in her loose bante dress.
There were vine leaves in her hair. The purple spilled from the cup she was
holding. The carnations of the painting had withered, but the eyes were still
wonderful in their depth and brilliancy of color They seemed to follow him wherever he
went. Yet one had ancestors in literature as well as in one’s own race, nearer
perhaps in type and temperament, many of of them, and certainly with an influence
of which one was more absolutely conscious. There were times when it
appeared to Dorian Gray that the whole of history was merely the record of his
own life, not as he had lived it in act and circumstance, but as his imagination had
created it for him, as it had been in his brain and in his
passions. He felt that he had known them all, those strange terrible figures that
had passed across the stage of the world and made sin so marvelous and evil so
full of subtlety. It seemed to him that in some mysterious way their lives had been his
own. The hero of the wonderful novel that had so influenced his life had himself
known this curious fancy and, as Caligula, had caroused with the green shirted jockies in their
stables and SED in an ivory manger with a jewel front leted horse; and, as
demission had wandered through a corridor lined with marble mirrors,
looking round with haggard eyes for the reflection of the dagger that was to end
his days, and sick with that onwe that terrible tedium Vita that comes on those
to whom life denies nothing; and had peered through a clear emerald at the
red shambles of the circus and then, in a litter of pearl and purple drawn by
silver shod mules, been carried through the Street of Pomegranates to a House of
Gold and heard men cry on Nero Caesar as he passed by; and, as Elagabalus, had
painted his face with colors and plied the distaff among the women, and brought
the Moon from Carthage and given her in mystic marriage to the
[Music]
son Petro Riario, the young Cardinal Archbishop of Florence, child and minion
of Sixtus IV., whose beauty was equaled only by his debauchery, and who received
Leonora of aragan in a pavilion of white and crimson silk, filled with nymphs and
Centaur and gilded a boy that he might serve at the feast as ganim or
hilas eelin whose melancholy could be cured only by the spectacle of death, and
who had a passion for red blood, as other men have for red wine— —the son of the
Fiend, as was reported, and one who had cheated his father at dice when gambling
with him for his own soul Jan Batista tibo who in mockery took the name of
Innocent and into whose torpid veins the blood of three lads was infused by a Jewish
doctor; Sigismondo Malatesta, the lover of isot and the lord of riny whose effigy
was burned at Rome as the enemy of God and man, who strangled Poca with a napkin,
and gave poison to genevra deste in a cup of emerald, and in honor of a
shameful passion built a pagan church for Christian worship; Charles II
who had so wildly adored his brother’s wife that a leper had warned him of the
insanity that was coming on him, and who, when his brain had sickened and grown
strange, could only be soothed by sarason cards painted with the images of love
and death and madness; and, in his trim jerkin and jeweled cap and a canthus
likee curls ginetto Bagon who slew asor with his bride, and simoneta with his
page, and whose comeliness was such that, as he lay dying in the yellow Piaza of
Perugia, those who had hated him could not choose but weep an Atalanta, who had
cursed him, blessed him. There was a horrible fascination in
them all. He saw them at night, and they troubled his imagination in the
day. The Renaissance knew of strange manners of poisoning— —poisoning by a
helmet and a lighted torch, by an embroidered glove and a jeweled fan, by a gilded pomander
and by an amber
chain. Dorian Gray had been poisoned by a book. There were moments when he looked
on evil simply as a mode through which he could realize his conception of the